<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fed | Capital Generating Assets]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/categories/fed/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-31T20:21:41+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.danielgelbart.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Gelbart]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Printing Money Without Causing Inflation, for Now.]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/2015/05/31/printing-money-without-causing-inflation/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-31T16:20:21+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/2015/05/31/printing-money-without-causing-inflation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--more-->


<p>After a huge stimulatory push by the Fed;  six years of interest rates at zero, and more than 4 Trillion dollars created by the Quantitative Easing program (or simply “QE”), we have witnessed a massive creation of new money. Perhaps the most important, as well as most substantiated economic theory, is that of inflation. Simply put, it states that more money in the economy results in more inflation. This begs the question: why is inflation so low?</p>

<p>There are only two possible explanations for this low inflation. Either the economy has grown enormously and in pace with the creation of new money, or, that this new money was created but is not circulating in the economy. The first option is clearly not the case, so we are left with the second. Indeed, for there to be inflation, the median income must rise. Since it has not, it indeed looks as if all this newly created money is “stuck” somewhere. To find where it is hiding, we need to “follow the money”.</p>

<p>The mechanism used by the Fed to infuse new money into the world, is to buy various securities from financial institutions. These are mostly government bonds, but as part of QE, also included mortgage backed securities. By buying these securities from financial institutions, the Fed is supplying those institutions with cash. The idea is that banks will use this money to provide loans to the public and to business, thus “stimulating the economy”. Some of the money provided by the Fed has indeed gone this way. It is of note that most large businesses have been loading up on debt. Mortgage rates have dropped, providing cheap loans to the public as well. But since median income has not risen significantly, the money is not freely flowing out of banks.</p>

<p>One very important role of the Federal reserve as a central bank, is that it requires banks to hold 10% of  their deposits on reserve at the Fed (and this is also the source of it&rsquo;s name). This is done to insure the availability of cash in hopes of avoiding bank failure in the situation of rapid deposit withdrawal. This means that banks are required to NOT lend out at least 10% of their deposits. Since banks make money from lending, banks only hold the required minimum amount on reserve at the Fed, choosing to lend out the remainder at the highest rate they can.</p>

<p>This all changed in 2008. As of yesterday, there are more than 2.5 Trillion dollars held held in EXCESS of the required minimum. That&rsquo;s a lot of money. It&rsquo;s almost one quarter of the entire amount of  money in circulation in the United States. And it&rsquo;s just sitting there, idly, not circulating in the economy. This money was not always there. Such huge deposits at the Federal reserve, are a recent development. In the 50 years before 2008, excess reserves at the Fed never exceeded 15 Billion dollars, or less than 0.6% of what they currently are.</p>

<p><img src="/images/FedReserves.png" title="&lsquo;excess federal reserves over time&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>So what happened?</p>

<p>In 2006, Congress passed legislation that allowed the Fed to pay banks interest on money they deposited at the Federal Reserve. In 2008, the Fed, in its role as lender of last resort, acted quickly to provide money to the failing financial system, and prevented it from imploding. The Fed also understood that the infusion of so much new money into the world would inevitability cause inflation. The Fed then, for the first time ever, used it&rsquo;s new authority to pay interest on deposits held at the Fed. This created two options for banks to collect interest on their money. The first option is the one they always had; the  interest payment on overnight loans to other banks, on deposits held at the Fed (the good old “Federal interest rate”). This rate averaged about 0.13% over the past six years. The second option available to banks, is the new interest payed to them directly by the Fed, on any deposits they have at the Federal reserve. This interest rate was set at 0.25%. While this is a very low rate, it is still double what can be achieved from inter bank loans. Whats more, all this is taking place during a time when banks are very reluctant to lend money (that&rsquo;s why the Fed had to act so drastically in the first place). In this environment, where banks don&rsquo;t want to lend, the Fed is buying securities from them (as part of QE), and at the same time promising to pay interest on any funds deposited back at the Fed, banks started depositing huge amounts of money at the Federal Reserve. Since the Fed is also the source of this money, it is as if the money never even left the Fed.</p>

<p>So that is how we ended up with a huge creation of new money, but with so much of it simply stock piling at the Fed and never leaving it. The Fed has been very successful at both preventing a collapse of the financial system, and at restoring confidence that it will continue to do whatever it takes to provide financial stability. By paying interest on deposits, the Fed has also been extremely successful at controlling the flow of currency, and keeping inflation low throughout a period of massive stimulation. Theses two achievements, are both extremely impressive, and of the highest importance.</p>

<p>But there is still a long road ahead. The Fed must continue dealing with the untangling of the current situation. The Quantitative Easing program ended in 2014. The next step is to gradually raise interest rates back to sustainable levels. This will begin in the next few months and interest rates will rise above 0.25% some time in the coming 12 months. When interest rates cross that level, banks will no longer be so eager to hold excess reserves at the Fed, and we will see the massive 2.5 Trillion dollar pile of money exit the Federal reserve. Such an opening of the flood gates will surly cause high inflation, probably into double digits on an annual basis.</p>

<p>The Fed still has the authority to pay interest on these funds, and it can raise it&rsquo;s payment above 0.25%. So we are sure to see the Fed attempting a very tricky financial dance. They will try to raise the interest they pay on deposits, in step with raising the (inter bank loan) interest rate target. On the one hand, the Fed will allow the accumulated excess funds to disperse into the economy, while at the same time carefully keeping their foot on the breaks, so that the money flows out slowly enough as to not cause very high inflation. To do so, the Fed will need to constantly adjust it&rsquo;s rate targets, while all the time keeping a close eye on inflation. This is no easy task, and it will take years, if not decades to carry out. With such a huge creation of new money behind us, we are sure to see higher inflation over the next ten years. Let&rsquo;s hope that the Fed can manage this new phase of financial recuperation as successfully as they have been managing the crisis up till now, and that it can continue to keep inflation down as much as possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
