<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Stock Market Valuation | Contango]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/categories/stock-market-valuation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-22T16:01:51+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.danielgelbart.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Gelbart]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interest Rates and Their Effect on Stock Prices]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/2015/04/22/interest-rates-and-their-effect-on-stock-prices/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-22T15:02:18+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.danielgelbart.com/blog/2015/04/22/interest-rates-and-their-effect-on-stock-prices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following more than six consecutive years with a federal funds rate of zero, the Fed has indicated that they are looking to raise interest rates some time before the end of 2015. When interest rates will go up, stock prices will be pulled down. There are multiple reasons for this affect. One way that stock prices are affected by higher interest rates, is that higher interest rates translate into more expensive loans, making the recycling of debt, as well as new debt more expensive. Another is that government bonds become a more attractive investment, and therefore divert money away from other investments. Higher interest rates can therefore result in less money flowing into the stock market, resulting in lower demand for stocks, and lower prices.</p>

<p>In addition, since this relationship is widely known, a broad expectation of future lower price levels forms whenever a broad expectation of future higher interest rates forms. The strongest cause of such future expectation, is if interest rates rise in the present. For this reason, we are sure to see a drop in stock market price levels immediately following the rate raise announcement from the Fed. This drop in prices, at least in the short term, will be greater than the true economic affect of rate change, as it will be largely due to money managers attempting to avoid future (expected further) price decline. A self fulfilling prophecy of sorts.</p>

<p>This short term drop in market price levels is a sure thing. The extent of it is hard to predict, as it will be the result of an automatic response, which will be amplified by later heard like behavior. The longer term affects will depend on the longer term interest rates to follow in the years to come.</p>

<p>In the long term, the general weight rising interest rates will have on the market, will be relative to the duration of them rising, as well as the duration of a “high&#8221; interest rates environment. That is, the affect of interest rates on price levels is a cumulative one. The more time rates are rising (or not declining) the stronger the affect.</p>

<p>By far the most powerful determinant of stock prices are earnings. Over the past century, stocks have generally traded at around 15 times earnings. Interest rates, once established over a period of a few years, will push this multiple higher or lower. In periods of low interest rates (as we are in right now) stocks may trade at an earnings multiple close to 20. While long periods of high interest rates can push the market downwards to trade at an earnings multiple lower than 15. Earnings do not stay constant over time. Over a short period of a couple years, earnings may decrease significantly or increase significantly. Generally, over the past century, earnings have increased slightly every year, even after allowing for inflation.</p>

<p>To get a broader picture of what can be expected in the US stock market over the next ten to twenty years, lets assume that earnings, overall, will continue to increase slightly at a rate of 2% a year (which is a reasonable to optimistic future). This means earnings will increase by about 20% (in total) in ten years, and by 50% in twenty. If interest rates increase significantly (say to above 8%) over this period, we can assume that stocks will trade at a lower multiple of earnings. If, for example they trade at around 12 times earnings, the market will see trading at price levels about 25% lower than today, ten years from now, and about 10% lower than today twenty years from now.</p>

<p>Under lower interest rates of around 2-6% over the next twenty years, while still assuming earnings will grow by 2% every year. If we guess stocks will trade at a multiple of 16, then ten years from now stocks will trade at roughly the same prices as they do today. Under these same assumptions stocks will be trading about 20% higher in twenty years, which works out to just under a 1% annual return.</p>

<p>Bottom line: You can safely expect a drop in stock prices to immediately follow the upcoming announcement from the Fed that they are raising their target for the federal funds rate. What will happen afterwards, strongly depends on the Fed&rsquo;s management of interest rates in the years to come. If stocks are bought at current prices, then even under relatively positive assumptions of consistent increases in corporate earnings as well as relatively low interest rates, returns can be expected to be low over the next ten to twenty years.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
